Hi. Good morning.
早上好
I'm so glad that you came.
很高兴你们都来了
I was worried that no one would show up in this weather.
我还担心在这种天气没人会来
I'm glad you are Ok.
很高兴你们都很好
Just a couple of announcements.
首先做几个声明
Questions that I received via email.
我通过邮件收到的几个问题
A few things before we jump into the material.
在开始课程之前我要说的几件事情
First of all,I was asked,"who is this class for?
首先 有人问我"这门课程是为谁设置的?"
Is it for people-- you know it's positive psychology --
"这是积极心理学"
people that are very unhappy?
"它是为非常不开心的人设置的吗?"
Is it only for people who are depressed?
"它只是为抑郁的人设置的吗?"
who is this class for?"
"这门课程是为谁设置的?"
Well,the class is for anyone who is interested in
这门课程的授课对象是
Positive psychology and anyone who wants to be happier.
对积极心理学有兴趣的人及想更开心的人
If you are extremely happy,you can still be happier.
如果你非常开心 你还可以更开心
If you are very unhappy,you can still be happier.
如果你非常不开心 你也可以更开心
so the class essentially is for anyone
所以这门课程适合任何
who's interested in the material-
对它感兴趣的人
and I would add someone who is really interested to work,
我会邀请有兴趣投入
to put the kind of effort that we talked about last time.
我们上次谈到的那种努力的人上来
Just not the kind of effort that we would require you to
你不需要投入那种
wreck your head about understanding certain concept,
为了明白某个概念而大为头痛的努力
but it is effort in terms of applying these ideas to your lives.
而是努力把这些观念融入你的生活
Now you may want to take this class,
也许你之所以上这门课程
because you are interested on academic level in positive
是因为你对积极心理学的理论感兴趣
psychology that's perfectly fine.
这也没问题
And you'll get many--
你将会得到很多...
we'll talk about numerous studies in every lecture,
我们每节课都会谈到非常多的研究
starting next time.
从下节课开始
We'll talk about study after study after study,
我们将接二连三地谈到那些研究
so you'll get that element as well.
所以你也可以得到理论方面的知识
However,if you are thinking about taking positive psychology
但是 如果你修积极心理学
for personal benefits,you need to put the effort in.
是为了个人利益 那么你就需要努力
And I'll talk more about that today.
对此今天我会作进一步的阐述
So the class is for everyone.
所以这门课程任何人都可以修
Anyone who's extremely happy and wants to be happier,
包括那些非常开心而且想更开心的人
and anyone who's not happy and wants to be happier.
及那些不开心但是想更开心的人
Pass/fail-- perfectly fine.
考试成绩 这不是个问题
Again the idea about this class is first and foremost for you.
这门课程的宗旨以你们的利益为上
So I would urge you if you do take pass
所以我建议如果你想及格
and fail to put in the work,
那么就要努力
and that's why the one element of pass/fail is not negotiable is
因此是否及格的决定因素之一
that all the response papers have to be submitted.
就是所有的回应报告必须交上来
Now the response papers,as you know,are not graded.
回应报告不会评分
They are basically reflection papers.
它们基本上就是心得体会
Will you reflect about the ideas about things
也就是你会思考能够融入
that can be applied to your life?
你的生活的想法和事情吗?
But they are required.
它们是必需要交的
So you hand them in,you pass.
你交上来 你就及格
If you don't hand them in,you fail.
不交就不及格
But other than that,by all means,
除此之外
if you want to take this class pass/fail,it's perfectly fine.
如果你想参加考试 那也没问题
Third thing,
第三件事
you'll be exposed to many theories,to many ideas in this class.
在这门课程你将会接触很多理论和观点
Not everything would resonate of you.
不是所有理论观点都会引起你的共鸣
There's a wonderful book just came out in 2008,
2008年出版了一本很棒的书
just two weeks ago,called "The How of Happiness"
就在两周前 书名叫《快乐之道》
by Sonja Lyubomirsky.
它由Sonja Lyubomirsky所著
And there she talks about the concept--
在书中她谈到了一个概念...
she's a professor at Riverside (UC),
她是加州大学河滨分校的教授
Harvard college graduate and went to Stanford for graduate school
哈佛大学的毕业生 斯坦福大学的研究生
she talks about the importance of finding fit,
她谈到了找到"适合"的重要性
meaning the fit between certain technique,
也就是某种方法
or tool,or idea,and yourself.
某种工具 某种观点是否适合你
Not every idea,
并不是你听到的每种观点
not every study that you've heard about,
每种研究
not every intervention that you actually practice
以及你运用的每种介入方法...
and you will practice interventions in your life,
你在生活中将会运用介入方法
whether it's doing acts of kindness,
不管是作善举
whether it's expressing gratitude,
还是表达感激
whether it's physical exercising,whether it's journaling.
还是体育锻炼 还是写日记
You will do all these things throughout the semester.
这些事情你在整个学期里都要做
Not everything would be right for you.
然而并不是一切都适合你
You'll be exposed to it.
你将会接触它
You'll try it.
尝试它
And then you'll make up your mind,
然后你将作出决定
"yes,this is what I want to incorporate"
"对 我想把它融入到生活中"
or "no,this is just not relevant for me."
或者"不 它对我没什么意义"
So it's important to keep that in mind.
所以记住这一点很重要
Anything that I talk about is backed by research,
我所说的一切都有研究论证
but the research doesn't say it's right for everyone.
但是研究没有说它适合所有人
It says it's for most people or for many people;
它说这对于大多数人或者对于很多人
this has worked or it is working.
都有作用或者正在起作用
So again be an active participant in this class
所以你要积极参与到课程中
as opposed to passive recipient of a doctrine.
而非某种学说的被动接受者
And identify the things that work for you-- not everything.
鉴别哪些东西适合你...不是一切东西
I guarantee not everything will work for you,
我敢说并非一切东西都适合你
but a lot of things will.
但是有很多东西会适合你
Your response papers that I just mentioned earlier:
关于我之前提到的回应报告
they are due at 5 pm,sorry,
它们在下午五点钟就要交 很抱歉
you'll get them by 5 pm on Tuesday,starting next Tuesday.
从下周二开始你将在每周二下午五点收到
And they will be due at 5 pm on Sunday to your TF.
然后在周日下午五点前交到你的任务组
Again the response papers are usually for most people fun,
回应报告对大多数人来说
interesting and engaging activities.
都是有趣而好玩的活动
Not graded,just basically for you to reflect,
它不会评分 它让你去思考
for you to grow through them.
并通过它们去成长
Thesis writers.
要写论文的人
How many of you are thesis writers?
你们中有多少人要写论文?
Just so I get a show of hand here.
请举手让我看看
Ok,I am sorry. No I'm kidding.
好的 很抱歉 我没有在开玩笑
Thesis writers: you'll not need to take the midterms.
要写论文的人 你们不用参加期中考试
I know it's crunch time around that time-
我知道那段时间里非常紧张...
being through it myself here.
我自己也经历过那段时期
So you'll not have to take the midterm.
所以你们不用参加期中考试
Your final will account for more.
你的期末考占更多分数
Unless you want to take the midterm,
除非你想参加期中考试
of course you'll more than welcome to.
当然我们非常欢迎你参加
we won't throw you out of the classroom.
我们不会把你扔到教室外面
Your thesis writers may.
写论文的人可以不用参加
There'll be many announcements online.
网上将会有很多公告
Do check the website on the regular basis.
请经常查看网站
We communicate a lot of things. Instead of sending you emails,
我们会发布很多东西 而不是向你发邮件
we'll have the announcements.
我们会发布公告
Check them regularly,about 6 7 times a day.
需要经常查看一下 大概每天六七次
Just kidding.
这只是开玩笑
Once a day or once every two days is more than enough.
一两天一次就已经足够了
I'd like Before I do jump into the material
在开始课程之前...
and we have a very exciting lecture today,
今天的课程非常令人兴奋
to invite Deb Levy who is the head TF for extension school--
我们会邀请进修学院任务组组长Deb Levy
so extension school students,
哈佛进修学院的同学们
I know there are a couple of you here,
我知道该学院的一些同学在这里
those of you at home--
还有一些在家里...
here she is. Deb Levy.
有请 Deb Levy
Deb Levy:Alright.
好的
I have about 20,30 minutes to talk
我大概有二三十分钟的发言时间
so I'm gonna start with my childhood. I am just kidding.
所以我会从我小时候讲起...这只是开玩笑
I am the head TF for the extension school and we are thrilled.
我是进修学院的任务组组长 我们很激动
We have 296 extension students taking this course online,
进修学院有296名学生在选修这门课程
which means they are going to watch videos,
也就是说他们会收看视频
and then extension students
进修学院的学生们
you'll be in sections on teleconference,
你们会参加电话会议
When people are gonna call in,
人们会打电话进来
there are gonna be teleconferences
所以我们将会有电话会议
which is going to be a great opportunity.
这是个很好的机会
Let's say hi to people out there in New Zealand.
我们跟新西兰的人打声招呼
Hi. France. Kentucky. Lexington.
还有法国的 肯塔基州的 莱克星顿的人
It's really unbelievable.
真是难以置信
So the other thing is I want to take a picture actually.
另一件事就是 我想拍一张照片
(Tal: No pictures in the classroom.)
教室里不准拍照
You'll take a picture Tal.
也给你拍一张 Tal
So I am not going to do any lecturing.
我不会授课
But since Tal and I have very similar systematic stuff,
但是Tal和我有着相似的系统知识
so if Tal is absent for any reason,
所以如果Tal因某种原因缺席的话
I'll be doing the lecture for you.
我会代你授课
(Tal: Good.)
很好
The other is: people who are extension,
另一件事就是 进修学院的学生们
I want to you be patient.
希望你们要耐心点
We are going to get information out there as soon as we can.
我们会尽快把信息发出去
And you'll all be sectioned in next week or so.
大概下周你们就会分组
And feel thrilled to be here.
能来这里真是太激动了
Great. Thank you Deb.
好的 谢谢你 Deb
So I want to start with a story,
我想以一个故事开始今天的课程
something that happened to me exactly 2 years ago,
那是两年前发生在我身上的事
just about to the day,
恰好两年
when was the last time when I taught positive psychology.
那是我上次教积极心理学的最后一节课
As the semester started,
那学期开始的时候
it was a very stressful period also,my mentor,
同时那是压力很大的一个时期 我的导师
who I am dedicating this class as well as
我要把这节课程
all my future positive psychology class is to,
以及将来的积极心理学课程献给
Philip Stone passed away just the day before the class started.
在课程开始前一天去世的Philip Stone
Very stressful period.
那时候我压力非常大
And I got sick. And I got very sick.
我生病了 病得非常严重
Somehow I got through the class.
然而我还是上完了课
I taught the Thursday class. That started 2 years ago.
我教授周四的课程 它从两年前开始
It started on Tuesday. So I taught on Tuesday.
课程在周二上
Somehow Thursday,completely drugged.
后来改为周四 我服了很多药
This lecture I made it through somehow.
然而我还是上完了课
And I went to home  and I couldn't fall asleep.
我回家后无法入睡
I was in real pain. I went to the doctors.
我感到非常痛 所以我去看医生了
That was on Friday afternoon,just saying
那是周五下午 我说
"you know I have to go. The medication I took didn't help."
"我必须要看医生 我服的药不起作用"
Went to the doctors. Had some blood tests.
我去看了医生 验了血
And finally after days I couldn't sleep
几天无法入睡之后
because of pain,fell asleep.
由于痛苦我终于睡着了
This was Friday night.
那是周五晚上
In the midnight,there was a phone call.
午夜的时候电话响了
I don't hear it. I am fast asleep.
我没有去接 我很快睡着了
My wife picks it up. Tommy picks it up.
我的妻子Tommy拿起了话筒
It's the doctor.
那是医生打来的
And the doctor says to Tommy,
医生对Tommy说
"the test results just came in.
结果出来了
And Tal should get to the hospital now."
Tal要立刻到医院来
She said to the doctor,
她对医生说
"He just fell asleep. He hasn't slept for days.
他刚睡着 他几天没睡了
Can it wait til tomorrow morning?"
能不能等到明天再去?
And the doctor said,"No. And he has to go to Beth Israel,
医生说 不行 他要到Beth Israel医院
because they have the best labs for what he needs right now."
那里有最好的实验室可以给他提供治疗
And she doesn't elaborate it any more.
她没有再说
Tommy wakes me up,retells me the story of what's happening.
Tommy叫醒了我 告诉我发生的事
Somehow I get up.
我起来了
She can't take me to the hospital because David,
她不能带我去医院 因为David
at that time one year old,is asleep.
当时他才一岁 他正在睡觉
We don't want to wake him up.
我们不想叫醒他
So we get a cab to take me to Beth Israel.
我们叫了一辆计程车带我到Beth Israel医院
On the way-- so this was the year
路上...这是我不做
after I was no longer resident tutors in Leverett.
Leverett的常驻导师资格的第二年
We were (?),driving down the Charles River.
我们驶经查尔斯河
Up and drive and then next to Harvard.
然后我们经过哈佛
I look at Harvard. I look at the beautiful river.
我当时看着哈佛 看着美丽的河
It's very quiet.
四周静悄悄
Not many cars just after midnight on a Friday night.
周五午夜之后没有多少车辆
And I can't help myself but think,
我情不自禁地想
"what if there's something really terrible going on?"
如果情况真的很严重呢?
I mean,why would they call me midnight to the hospital--
他们为什么午夜叫我去医院
Beth Israel,insisting on just one specific hospital?
还指定是Beth Israel医院?
There must be something really wrong.
一定是出了很严重的问题
And my mind begins to wander.
我开始思考
And I say,
我说
"what if I only have a year left? What would I do in that year?"
如果我只剩下一年时间呢? 我在这一年里会做什么?
I become very sad because I think I won't see David grow up.
我变得非常伤心 因为我看不到David长大
I won't see-- I won't have any future children.
我以后再也不会有孩子
Be careful up there.
在上面要小心谨慎
And I become very wistful and sad.
我变得十分忧郁悲伤
And then I ask myself,"Ok so professionally,
然后我问自己 好的 在职业上
what would I want to do in that last year?"
我在最后一年想做什么?
So I know personally exactly what I'll do.
我知道在生活在我要做什么
I'll spend all the time that I can with my family.
我会用所有时间和家人一起度过
But professionally what do I want to accomplish in this year?
但是在职业上在这一年我想完成什么?
And my immediate response was
我的第一反应就是
I want to leave behind a coherent body of work,
我要留下一个系列的课程
a coherent course introducing people to positive psychology.
一个向人们介绍积极心理学的系列课程
While I arrived at the hospital,I had some more checks.
我到达医院之后再进行了一些检查
It ends up being nothing too serious.
结果是没什么严重情况
They put me on antibiotics.
他们让我服抗生素
And within a couple of days I am on the way to recovery.
几天之内我就开始复原了
I want to share with you today though why.
但是今天我要和你们探讨
Why is it the most important thing for me
为什么对我最重要的事情...
at that time and still today,
那时和现在都是如此
is to leave behind a coherent body of work
就是留下一系列
about positive psychology,
关于积极心理学的课程
to introduce you to this wonderful field?
向你们介绍这个奇妙的领域?
Why positive psychology?Why is it? Its own field?
为什么是积极心理学?为什么是这个领域?
Why is it not--well,just study happiness,
为什么不只是研究
wellbeing as part of social psychology or clinical psychology?
社会心理学或临床心理学的幸福?
Why have so many scholars around the world
为什么世界上这么多学者
united around this concept of positive psychology?
都在研究积极心理学这个概念?
So this is what I want to do today.
这是我今天要说的
In the year of 2000,a research was done by David Myers.
2000年 David Myers做了一项研究
Davis Myers,from Hope College-- some of you
霍普学院的David Myers 你们当中学过
who've studied social psychology may have read his textbook,
社会心理学的可能读过他的书
did research,looking at psychological abstracts.
他做了心理学概念方面的研究
What he looked at was the ratio
他研究的是
between "negative research" and "positive research".
"消极研究"和"积极研究"之间的比率
Here is what he found.
这是他的研究结果
From 1967 to year of 2000-
从1967年到2000年
this was around the time when positive psychology started,
这是积极心理学的形成期
what he found in the 33 years are over 5000 articles on anger,
他发现在这33年里有5000篇文章研究愤怒
5000 research articles on anger.
5000篇文章研究愤怒
He found over 41000 research articles on anxiety
超过41000篇文章研究焦虑
and over 54000 articles on depression.
还有超过54000篇研究抑郁
And then he looked at the positive words,positive research.
然后他看看积极的概念 积极的研究
He looked for research on joy.
他寻找关于快乐的研究
And he found staggering 415 studies.
他仅仅找到了415篇研究
It does get better.
情况会有所改善
He looked at research on happiness
他寻找关于幸福的研究
and he found close to 2000 articles on happiness in 33 years.
他发现在33年里有接近2000篇文章研究幸福
Life satisfaction came on top: over 2500 studies.
生活满意度研究最多 超过2500篇研究文章
Still,if you look at that,
但是 如果你看看
the negative studies versus the positive studies,
消极研究和积极研究的对比
the ratio that you get is 21 to 1.
你得到的比率是21比1
For every one article on some positive aspect,
每份研究某个积极方面
some positive element of life,
积极因素的文章
wellbeing,satisfaction,joy,happiness,
不管是研究健康 满意程度 快乐还是幸福
you get 21 articles on depression,anxiety,
都有21份消极方面的文章 包括抑郁 焦虑
schizophrenia,neurosis and so on.
精神分裂 神经衰弱等等
Ratio of 21 to 1.
21比1的比率
Very depressing ratio,I must admit.
我得承认这是非常令人郁闷的比率
In fact,it made me very angry and anxious.
实际上它让我非常生气和忧虑
Studies focus on,primarily on what doesn't work,
那些研究主要集中于不起作用的东西上
mostly on what doesn't work. And this is not a new phenomenon.
大部分都是这样 而且这也不是新现象
Here is something from Abraham Maslow,
这是Abraham Maslow写的一些东西
who we mentioned last time,
我们上次提到过他
talking about this phenomenon in 1954:
他在1954年谈到过这种现象
"The science of psychology has been far more successful
"心理学这一学科对于消极方面的研究"
on the negative than on the positive side.
"远比对于积极方面的研究成功"
It has revealed to us much about man's shortcomings,
"它向我们展示了人类的短处"
his illnesses,his sins,
"他的缺点 他的过失"
but little about his potentialities,his virtues,
"但很少谈到他的潜能 他的长处"
his achievable aspirations or his psychological height.
"他的实际愿望或精神高度"
It is as if psychology had voluntarily restricted itself to only
"好像心理学自愿固步自封"
half its rightful jurisdiction and that darker,meaner half."
"让自己仅限于研究黑暗低劣的一半"
So what does psychology study?
心理学研究什么?
I mean the psychology concentrators here know that,
学心理学的人
probably guess that.
可能会猜
We study a lot of prejudice.
我们大量地研究偏见
We study a lot depression and anxiety.
我们大量地研究抑郁和焦虑
We study a lot about conformity.
我们大量地研究相似性
We study a lot about misjudgments and errors,
我们大量地研究判断错误和过失
very much focusing on this aspect and very little--
大概就是专门研究这方面而很少...
again,21 to 1,very little-- on the positive.
21比1的比率表明很少研究积极方面
And when I look at this ratio and I think about it,
看到这个比率时 我想
this is 1954-- hasn't changed much since.
那是1954年 到现在也没多大改变
And when I think about it and I look into it,
当我思考它调查它的时候
I think that psychology needs help.
我觉得心理学需要帮助
I really do.
我真的这样觉得
I mean think about it at a personal level.
你可以从个人的角度想想它
that if you had a person who 21 hours a day was depressed
如果一个人一天里有21小时感到消沉
and one hour in a day felt good?
而只有一个小时感觉良好会怎样?
Or one day feeling good and then 21 days feeling anxious
或者有一天感觉良好 便有21天觉得焦虑
and depressed?
和消沉会怎样?
You would say that this person would need help.
你会说这个人需要帮助
And the field I think,needs help.
我觉得这个领域需要帮助
But the question becomes "is it the right analogy?"
但问题是 这是正确的比喻吗?
Should we look at it this way?
我们应该这样去看待它吗?
Because the 21 ratio is unhealthy,
因为21比1的比率是不健康的
certainly would be so on the individual level,
从个人的角度来看肯定也是这样
but it reflects reality in many ways.
但是它从多个角度反映了现实
Because what we are seeing today
因为我们今天所看到的
in more and more research showing that there is more and more
是越来越多的研究表明
depression around the world,
世界上出现了越来越多的抑郁症
that there is more and more anxiety,east,west,north,south--
还有越来越多的焦虑 东南西北
around the world.
世界各地
And one could argue--
有些人会争辩道...
people who argue for continuing to do research in this area,
那些主张继续研究这片领域
for doing less in positive psychologies,--
而少点研究积极心理的人认为
well we should be doing even more than the 21 to 1 ratio,
我们应该让这个比率大于21比1
because we want to alleviate the anxiety
因为我们想缓和人们受到的
and depression that people experience.
焦虑和抑郁
Today depression is 10 times higher than it was in 1960.
今天的抑郁症病例比1960年高十倍
Now part of it is because there's more awareness,
部分的原因是人们的意识程度高了
because we measure better.
我们对抑郁症的诊断更准确
But that's not all.
但这并非全部原因
It's also simply because objectively there's more depression.
还因为抑郁症在客观上增加了
And one way of knowing that is that the most objective "measure"
其中的一种迹象就是 最客观的"诊断"
that we have is unfortunately suicide.
不幸的是 就是自杀
And numbers have risen significantly around the world,
自杀人数在世界范围内明显上升
not just in the United States--
不仅是在美国
whether it's in China,whether it's Australia-- as well as here.
不管是在中国 澳大利亚还是这里
The mean age for depression today is less than 15.
现在抑郁症人群的平均年龄小于15岁
Kids at very young age are introduced to the
孩子们在很小的时候就接触了
"information highway".
信息高速公路
And very often,they are not prepared,
通常来说他们都没有准备好
not able to deal with it in an effective way.
他们无法有效地应对它
So when we look at this data,
所以当我们看到这个数据时
we say we do need more research to help people
我们认为我们需要更多的研究帮助人们
overcome depression,to help people overcome anxiety.
克服抑郁症 克服焦虑
And I don't want to belittle that.
这应引起足够的重视
That is important. It is extremely important.
这非常重要 极度的重要
What I'm arguing,what I will argue for,
我主张的
is the shift of the pendulum.
是天平的偏移
So it's no longer 21 to 1.
这样它将不会再是21比1
There are more,many more studies in positive psychology,
要有更多的研究关于积极心理学
-- not to the exclusion of,not at all,
不是要只研究它 根本不是
but just shifting the pendulum.
而是让天平偏移一点
How about here?
这里的情况如何?
In our local village?
我们的象牙塔里的情况如何?
This article,-- I couldn't find a study that is more recent,
有一篇文章...我无法找到更新的研究
this was published in 2004.
它是在2004年发表的
Harvard Crimson (http://www.thecrimson.com/).
《哈佛克里姆森》
This article says that,in their 6 months study of this,
这篇文章说 经过他们6个月的研究
80% of Harvard students experienced depression
哈佛大学八成的学生在过去一年
over the past year.
都经历过抑郁期
Now we are not talking about the regular ups and downs
我们说的不是大多数人一天里
that most people have ten times a day-- I certainly do.
经常出现的情绪起伏 我也是如此
We are talking about depression here.
我们说的是抑郁
For an extended period of time.
它会持续一段时间
47% of Harvard students,according to this,--
根据这份研究 47%的哈佛学生...
and grant it: this is not academic study,
这不是学术研究
but I will share with you academic study in a minute,
但是我待会就和你们分享学术研究
published in a top-tier refereed journal.
它发表在高级期刊上
But Crimson has founded in its survey
但是克里姆森里的研究表明
that 47% Harvard students over the past year
47%的哈佛学生在过去一年
have experienced depression to the point of not functioning.
经历过无法正常生活学习的抑郁期
So they couldn't leave home.
他们无法出门
They were really struggling to just basically get through the day.
他们要痛苦地度日
47%.
47%的人
Now when people look at this,they say
人们看到这个数据的时候 他们说
"well of course,we need to focus more on psychopathology.
"当然了 我们要努力研究精神病理学"
21 to 1-- not enough! 30 to 1 sounds more like it."
"21比1还不足够 30比1才像样"
We see it around campuses.
这样的情况各个校园都有
This is not peculiar to Harvard.
而不仅仅是哈佛
Not at all peculiar to Harvard.
绝对不是哈佛才有的现象
Richard Kadison,
Richard Kadison
who is the head of mental health services here,
他是这里的心理健康服务中心的领导
in the New England Journal of Medicine--
他最近在医学领域的领先杂志
probably the leading journal in the field of Medicine,
《新英格兰医学杂志》上
recently published an article,
发表了一篇文章
where he talked about a survey
他谈到了一项调查
that was done among 13500 college students nationwide,
调查对象是全国13500名大学生
different kinds of colleges,
他们来自不同类别的学院
universities,states schools,private schools.
大学 公立学校 私立学校
And what they found in this very significant study
他们在这项重要的研究里发现
was that 45% of college students nationwide over the past year
全国45%的大学生在过去一年
have experienced depression to the point of not functioning.
经历过无法正常生活学习的抑郁期
So The Harvard Crimson found 47;
《哈佛克里姆森》的数据是47%
nationwide,it was 45-- essentially identical,
在全国范围的数据是45% 基本上是一样
no significant difference among the two.
两者之间的差异并不大
This is a nationwide phenomenon.
这是一个全国性的现象
In this study,
这份研究表明
94% of college students nationwide feel overwhelmed
全国94%的大学生感到压抑
and stressed by everything that they have to do.
因为他们必须要做的事而不堪负重
94%.
94%
I mean these are supposed to be the best four years of our lives.
这本应该是我们一生中最美好的四年
Something is going on here.
事情不对劲
Now this is not unique to United States.
不仅是美国才有这种现象
I just recently came back from a tour.
我最近刚从一次游历回来
I was in-- spent time in Europe-- in the UK,France;
我到了欧洲 包括英国 法国
spent a lot of time in China and some time in Australia.
我在中国逗留了很久 也去了澳洲
In every one of these places,
所有这些地方
the governments are really concerned;
政府都非常担忧...
university presidents are very concerned
大学校长们都非常担忧
about the growing level of depression,
越来越多的抑郁现象
anxiety and general mental disorder,
焦虑 精神紊乱
rise of suicide rates in all of these countries that I mentioned.
自杀率的上升 上面提到的所有国家都是如此
So we have a global epidemic here.
所以这是全球性流行病
And once again going back so: Is it the 21:1 ratio good?
我们再看看 21比1的比率是好事吗?
Is it important? Shouldn't it be increased?
它重要吗?它不是应该扩大吗?
How can we even think about studying happiness
我们怎么可以去研究幸福
and well-being and love and joy?
健康 爱和快乐?
Shouldn't we first deal with
我们不是应该首先处理
the real pressing problem of depression,
真正迫切的问题吗? 比如抑郁
anxiety,neurosis and so on?
焦虑 神经衰弱等等
--Some truth to that,
这样说确实有些道理
but again what I'm going to argue for in this class
但是在这个课程里我要主张的是
is that we do need to also,
我们也要...
not only,not exclusively,not even necessarily primarily,
不是专门 也不用主要
we need to also focus on the positive.
我们也要集中研究积极心理学
I am going to talk about three reasons why we should do that.
我要说三个为什么应该这样做的理由
The first reason is that it is important to focus on what works,
首先 集中研究有用的东西至关重要
because what works or what we focus on rather creates reality.
因为有用的或者集中研究的会成为现实
If we focus on what is working,
如果我们集中研究起作用的
we'll have more working in our world,
它就会在世界起更大的作用
more working in ourselves,more working in our relationships.
在我们身上以及关系上起更大作用
The second reason why positive psychology
其次 为什么积极心理学
as an independent field of study as a course in
作为一门独立领域的研究学科
and of itself is important is that being happy
是重要的 这是因为快乐
is not just the negation of happiness.
并非只是对痛苦的否定
It doesn't mean just get rid of depression or anxiety
摆脱我正在经历的
that I am experiencing,
抑郁或者焦虑并不意味着
I spontaneously become happy.
我同时就变得快乐了
That's not the case. That's not how it works.
情况并非是这样 问题不会这样被解决
And finally,prevention which is very important today,
最后 预防在今天来说非常重要
the most effective way of preventing hardship,
预防困苦最有效的方法...
-- whether it's depression,whether it's anxiety,
不管是抑郁还是焦虑
-- is actually by focusing on and cultivating the positive.
实际上是通过专注于培养积极心态
Now I will share with you some studies about this.
我会跟你们分享一些关于这点的研究
So for these three reasons,we need positive psychology.
这三个原因表明我们需要积极心理学
Let me begin with the importance of focusing on what works.
我从专注于有效方法的重要性开始
In the introduction to the Handbook of Positive Psychology,
在《积极心理学手册》的序言里
Martin Seligman who we talked about last time,
我们上次提到的Martin Seligman...
considered the father of positive psychology,
他被认为是积极心理学之父
network of scholars,says this:
影响了很多学者 他说
"The aim of positive psychology is to catalyze a change
"积极心理学的目标是促成一种变化"
in psychology from a preoccupation only with repairing the worst
"让心理学从只关注补救生活中最糟糕的事"
things in life to also building the best qualities in life."
"到同时建立生活中最美好的事"
Note that he says also.
请留意他说的是同时
He doesn't say exclusively or even primarily.
他没有说专门 甚至没有说主要
It's important to focus on what works,
专注于研究有效的东西至关重要
-- whether it is in our relationship,whether it's in ourselves,
不管是对我们的关系 对我们自身
whether it's in others,whether it's in Harvard,
对其他人 对哈佛
whether it's in United States or the world--
对美国还是对世界而言
in order to have more what works.
这是为了获得更多有效的东西
Now the question is "how do we focus on what works?"
问题是"如何专注于研究有效的东西?"
And the answer to this question
这个问题的答案
is through the questions that we ask.
就在我们提出的问题的本身
Let me illustrate through a case study.
我通过一个案例研究来阐明这点
Psychologists,starting in the late 1940s,
心理学家在20世纪40年代末开始
studied at-risk population.
研究受危人群
More and more money-- government money,university money,
越来越多的钱 政府资金 大学资金
philanthropist money-- went into study in the cities or places
慈善基金都投入到研究城市或地区里
where generally the kids were considered at risk--
所谓的受危儿童的身上
more prone to dropping out of school,
他们更容易退学
more prone to later-on crime,teen pregnancy and so on.
以后更容易犯罪 少女妊娠等等
So this study they put in a lot of money,
他们为这项研究投入了大量金钱
a lot of effort into this.
大量的精力
The question that the psychologists asked was
心理学家们问的问题是
"why do these individuals fail?
"为什么这些人会失败"
why does such a high percentage of students in
"为什么受危人群中"
that as-risk population end up dropping out of school?
"有如此高比例的学生退学?"
Getting pregnant? Crime?"
"怀孕?犯罪?"
--And we'll talk about the statistics later on next week.
我们下周再谈统计数据
"Why do so many of these individuals fail?"
"为什么他们当中有这么多人会失败?"
Now an important question,
他们提出了很重要的问题
good intentions of the psychologists,smart people,lot of money,
心理学家们动机良好 头脑灵活 投入了很多钱
lot of resources going in.
投入了很多资源
However,very little change was introduced.
然而 变化却非常少
Very little change came about as results of these studies.
这些研究带来的变化微乎其微
And the situation in many areas continued to exacerbate.
很多地区的情况继续恶化
Certain didn't get any better,despite the good intentions,
情况没有任何好转 虽然动机良好
despite the resources,despite the brain power
虽然资源充足 虽然人们头脑灵活
that twined into the researching into this question.
它们都被投入去研究这个问题
Interesting answers--
得到的答案却非常有意思
well,we need better education,we need better buildings,
我们需要更好的教育 更好的建筑
we need more resources,
更多的资源
but very little change actually in practice came about.
但是实际上发生的变化很少
And then there was a paradigm,
然后出现了一种范式
quite literally a paradigm shift in the 1980s.
20世纪80年代出现了范式转移
Through the work of Antonovsky who I mentioned last time
通过Antonovsky的努力 我上次提到过他
and I'll mention again today,through the work of Antonovsky,
今天我要再次提到他 通过Antonovsky
and other people like Ellen Langer,other people like Alice Isen,
及Ellen Langer和Alice Isen等其他人的努力
different questions started to be asked by psychologists.
心理学家们提出了不同的问题
Instead of asking what did these individuals fail,
他们不去问为什么这些人会失败
positive psychologists started to ask what made some individuals
积极心理学家开始问是什么让某些人
succeed despite unfavorable circumstances?
成功了?即便面对的是不理想的环境?
Maybe it was the case that many failed,but not everyone.
也许是有很多人失败了 但并非所有人
Some succeeded and succeeded big time.
有些人成功了 而且非常成功
And what psychologists started to do then was to ask why.
心理学家们此时便开始问 为什么
What is it about them that is so successful?
为什么他们如此成功?
And that,in the words of Frost,made all the difference.
用Frost的话来说 这才是至关重要的
The psychologists started to identify elements,
心理学家们开始识别这些人的各种因素
aspects of these individuals and studied them in depth,
以及各个方面并深入分析他们
starting to study the successful individuals,
他们开始研究这些成功的人
and identify elements that they could then teach later
并识别出各种因素
in creating interventions based on what they had studied.
然后他们通过研究想出介入方法
And suddenly,there were results,real results,
突然间结果出来了 真正的结果
tangible results,after decades of virtually zero results,
切实的结果 打破了数十年零结果的局面
simply based on the question.
这仅仅是基于一个简单的问题
And the main concept that came out at that time,
那时候出现的主要概念
through the research of these psychologists
通过这些心理学家的研究
who started to ask the positive question,
正是他们开始问积极的问题
started to focus on what is working on the successful children.
开始专注于研究成功的孩子们
The concept that came out was the concept of resilience.
那时出现的概念是心理弹性
Now today everyone talks about resilience.
现在大家都在谈心理弹性
We talk about resilience in school,
我们在学校谈心理弹性
at work,in the job,in the bedroom.
在工作上谈 在卧室里谈
Everywhere resilience.
在哪里都谈心理弹性
However,at that time in the 1980s,
然而 在20世纪80年代
very few people even talked about or knew what that means.
很少人谈及甚至很少人知道它的意思
When they studied resilience,which is defined as following,
研究心理弹性的时候 它被定义如下
it made all the difference.
它的定义关系重大
Resilience,--
心理弹性
a class of phenomena characterized by patterns of positive
一种现象 特征是积极适应的模式
adaptation in the context of significant adversity or risk.
即使是面对非常不利或危险的环境
These kids,who succeeded-- ended up succeeding,
这些成功的孩子最终成功了
and they look through longitudinal studies--
这是通过纵向研究得出的结论
5 years later,10 years,30 years later,
五年后 十年后 三十年后
the kids who succeeded,were resilient.
这些成功的孩子都具有适应力
Initially,when they studied these kids,
一开始 当他们研究这些孩子时
the assumption was these must be super kids,extraordinary kids,
他们认为这些孩子一定很优秀
one in a hundred,one in a thousand-
百里挑一甚至千里挑一
not really replicable,therefore.
因此是不可以模仿的
However,
然而
what they found when they continued to study
当他们继续研究
those people who work,those people who succeeded,
这些成功的人时 继续研究虽然环境不理想
despite the unfavorable circumstances,
然而仍然成功的人时
-- what they found was these were not super kids.
他们发现这些并非是非常优秀的孩子
In fact these were ordinary kids with ordinary characteristics
实际上这些是普通的孩子 他们性格普通
that led to extraordinary results.
但是成就非凡
For example,let me share with you some of the things.
例如 我告诉你们几件事
These kids were optimistic,
这些孩子都很乐观
-- not optimistic in the detached Pollyannish sense,
不是那种不切实际的盲目乐观
-- optimistic in that they believe in things
而是乐观地相信
that would work out well,
事情会被圆满地解决
and we'll talk a lot about optimism as an interpretation style,
我们会经常把乐观主义当作诠释谈及
in the work of Martin Seligman and karen Reivich.
也就是Martin Seligman和karen Reivich的乐观主义
They were optimistic in the sense of thinking,
他们的乐观在于认为
"well,it may not work well this time.
"好吧 也许这次不会成功"
It will work out later.
"它以后会成功的"
I have learned from what had just happened."
"我从刚发生的事学到了东西"
They had faith and sense of meaning in life.
他们对生活有信心 认为它有意义
Sometimes it was religious faith,not always.
有时它是宗教信仰 但却不总是这样
It was doing something that they really believed in.
这种信仰是做他们相信的事
Many of them were idealistic.
他们中很多人都是理想主义者
One of main topics we will discuss in this class is
我们在这门课程里谈及的话题之一
that to be idealistic is to be realistic,
就是理想主义就是现实主义
because we have a real internal need,innate need for idealism.
因为我们的内心需要理想主义
So these kids experienced sense of meaning,
所以这些孩子有"意义感"
whether it was meaning in terms of personal success
不管是个人成功方面的意义
and how I will make it,
以及他们的行事方式的意义
or sense of meaning in their community contributing,
或者是服务社区的意义
something meaningful in sense of purpose.
还有事情的目标意义
By the way,when I go through all these,
顺便说一下 我说的这一切
these are no less important for any other person in the world.
它们对所有人都一样重要
This resilience as we mentioned earlier
我们之前提到的心理弹性
is just not important for the at-risk population.
不但对受危人群很重要
It's as important at Harvard.
对哈佛大学里的人也一样重要
And not just during exam period.
也不仅是在考试期间重要
It's important that resilience is associated with wellbeing.
把心理弹性与幸福联系起来非常重要
So think about these characteristics and you display them.
思考这些特点 你就会展示它们
And the interesting thing about all these characteristics
我在这里提到的这些特点
they can all be learned.
你可以学到它们
that I'll mention here is that they can all be taught;
有趣的一点就是它们都可以习得
In many ways,this class is about that.
从多个方面来说 这门课程说的就是这个
And when the psychologists identified these,
当心理学家们识别出这些特点之后
they started to teach them and the individuals started to learn
他们开始教授它们 人们也开始学了
and that made all the difference.
情况便发生了变化
In addition to the faith and sense of meaning,
除了信心以及"意义感"
pro-social behavior,helping other people,
利社会行为 帮助他人
shifting from helplessness to helpfulness,they were significant.
从无助转变到有益 它们都非常重要
One of the things that we'll talk about is
我们要讨论的事情之一就是
how meaningful it is to help other people.
帮助他人的意义
And how much it doesn't just only help others,
它不但帮助他人
it also helps ourselves.
它还会帮助我们自己
And we enter an upward spiral between self-help and other-help.
我们便进入了自助和助他人的上升式螺旋里
Because when we help others,we are helping ourselves.
因为我们帮助他人时也在帮助自己
when we help ourselves,we help others.
当我们帮助自己时在帮助他人
And so on and so on.
循环往复
So they were pro-social.
所以他们都是利社会者
They were helping other people.
他们都在帮助别人
They focused on their strength
他们的眼光集中在自己的长处上
rather than primarily deficiencies.
而不是缺点
They did not ignore their weaknesses,but they asked,
他们不忽视自己的缺点 但他们会问
"what am I good at? What am I really,really good at?"
我真正擅长的是什么?
And again,part of this course,
重申一次 这门课程的目标之一
you'll identify your strength,
就是你会认清自己的长处
whether it's through online test,
不管是通过线上测试
whether it's through reflection papers,
通过回应报告
whether it's in section.
通过小组学习
You'll think about it whether it's through your readings.
还是通过阅读 你都会思考它
Identify the strength.
认清长处
What are they good at?
他们擅长的是什么?
They set goals for themselves.
他们为自己设立目标
They were future-oriented,
他们面向未来
not just thinking about how bad things are today perhaps,
他们不但思考事情现在有多糟糕
but also thinking about
同时也在思考
"this is where I wanna be 5 years or 10 years from now."
五年后或十年后的目标
We are going to devote three classes to goal setting,
我们会用三节课谈论设立目标
very significant part of resilience.
这是心理弹性的重要组成部分
They had a role model.
他们有一个榜样
Someone who they said about
他们会说
"I want to be like her; I want to be like him."
"我想像她那样 我想像他那样"
It could be a teacher. It could be a parent,sibling,friend.
榜样可以是老师 可以是亲戚朋友
Sometimes,
有时候
it was a historical figure or a fictional character,
它是一个历史人物或小说的人物
someone that they want to emulate,to be like.
一个他们可以效仿的人
That gave them strength. That gave them sense of direction.
榜样给予他们力量 给他们方向感
And finally,most significantly,they did not bowl alone.
最后 最重要的就是他们不单干
They had social support. They did not say :
他们有社会的支持 他们不会说
"well I am tough enough to do it by myself."
"我够能干 可以自己做"
Rather they said :"I'm tough enough to reach out for help."
他们说"我够能干 我可以请求帮助"
Because that does require certain toughness.
因为那确实需要某种能力
The strength to admit weaknesses as well,
还有承认弱点的勇气
the strength to admit a need.
承认有某种需要的勇气
Now think about these:
想想
do you have these things here for yourself at Harvard in life?
你在哈佛 在生活中你有这些东西吗?
And if not,you can cultivate all of these things,
如果没有 你可以培养这一切
whether it's a social support--
不管是社会支持...
and it doesn't have to be a hundred people
不用是每天
whom you talk to everyday;
与你交谈的一百人
it can be one or two close friends,mom,dad,roommates--
它可以是一两个好朋友 父母 室友
makes a big difference.
这至关重要
No. 1 contributor to resilience.
它是心理弹性最重要的因素
Now the important thing about social support
社会支持重要的一点
is identifying the right people.
就是找到适合的人
People who,when you reach out to them,
那些你向他们请求帮助
will reach back to you and will be able to give back.
便会给予回应的人
I want to show you an example now of a not so good role model
现在我向你们展示一个并不太好的榜样
for social support.
不太好的社会支持
And that is an interaction
这是Grace和Karen之间的一段交流
between Grace and Karen from Will and Grace.
视频片断来自剧集《Will and Grace》
Will and Grace (From Episode 309):
《Will and Grace》（第3季第9集）
SALESMAN: This video game makes a nice birthday gift.
这台游戏机是份不错的生日礼物
Do you think your stepson would like that?
你觉得你的继子会喜欢吗?
KAREN: I don't know,honey.
我不知道 亲爱的
Can he eat it or rub up against it?
他可以吃它或者摩擦它吗?
SALESMAN: Let's come at this a different way.
我们换一种方式了解
What are his interests?
他的兴趣是什么?
KAREN: Ham.
火腿
SALESMAN: Why don't I just let you browse awhile?
还是你自己到处看看吧
KAREN: Yeah. Thanks. Ooh,and,uh,
好的 谢谢
do you think there's anything you could do
你可以处理一下
about all these kids in here?
这些小孩吗?
SALESMAN: Ma'am,it's a toy store.
夫人 这是玩具店
KAREN: Yeah. See what you can do.
好的 处理一下
Move it,shorty.
别挡道 矮个子
GRACE: Hi,Karen. Um...
Karen
I can't help you shop today. I've gotta go.
今天我不能和你买东西了 我得走了
KAREN: What's going on? What's happening?
怎么回事?发生什么事了?
What's with the geisha hand?
为什么要装害羞?
GRACE: Nothing.
没什么
I just had something zapped at the dermatologist's,
我在皮肤科医生那里做了点手术
and it looks kinda funky,
看起来有点恐怖
and I just don't want anyone to see it right now.
现在我不想任何人看到它
KAREN: Grace,
Grace
I'm sure it's not nearly as bad as you think it is.
我敢说它并没有你想的那么糟糕
It's probably nothing,a little dot. Come on. Show mama.
也许不值一提 一个小点 让妈妈看看
KAREN: Aah! Whoa! Oh! Oh,my God! Oh!
啊 我的天啊
GRACE: Shh! Shhhhh! Karen,Will you calm down?
嘘 Karen 冷静下来
KAREN: How do you expect me to calm down
你叫我怎么冷静下来?
when I can see its heart beating right in front of me?! Aah!
我看到它的心脏在我面前跳动
GRACE: Shh!
嘘
KAREN: Well,uh,alright.
好的
Alright,I'm sorry.
好的 非常抱歉
So how long have you had the herpes?
你患疱疹多久了？
GRACE: It's not herpes.
这不是疱疹
It's not even herpes adjacent.
它跟疱疹挨不着边
KAREN: Oh,yeah? Well,
是吗?
it's close enough to be invited to the herpes family picnic.
它可以参加疱疹的家庭野餐了
GRACE: It was a weird freckle,
这是一个奇怪的雀斑
and the doctor wanted to freeze it,
医生想要冻结它
and then he told me that it was going to take 10 days to heal.
然后他告诉我要十天才能复原
I mean,what made him assume that I could look awful for 10 days?
他怎么会认为我可以丑陋十天?
Respond to that,and I will rub it all over your Prada.
因此 我要拿着你的尼龙包擦它
KAREN: What are you lookin' at,prego?
你在看什么 大肚婆?
Haven't you ever seen herpes before?
以前没见过疱疹吗?
Jeez. Fat people are so insensitive
天啊 胖子真是麻木不仁
GRACE: Oh,my God. Oh,my God.
我的天啊 我的天啊
Would you look at it in this little toy mirror?
从这块小玩具镜照出来的样子看来
It's gotten...bigger. It's like Barbie's dream zit.
它变大了 就像芭比梦想中的青春痘
Thank God I canceled my date with Mark.
幸亏我取消了和Mark的约会
KAREN: Yeah,'cause that thing looks like
没错 因为它看起来
it needs orange cones and police tape around it.
要交通柱和警察拦护带才能遮住
GRACE: Come on. Let's get outta here.
来吧 我们离开这里
So Karen may not be a good choice for social support.
Karen也许不是社会支持的好选择
But there are many people who are.
但是有很多人却是好的选择
Now think about the power of the question.
想想一个问题的力量
Think about what a question did.
想想一个问题带来的结果
For decades,
数十年间
many kids who potentially could have been helped weren't helped,
很多可以得到帮助的人没有得到
because the right question was not asked as well.
因为没有提出正确的问题
And it was only after positive question,
只有在积极问题...
the focusing on the positive question was asked
专注于积极的问题被提出来后
that suddenly psychologists were able to see
心理学家们突然能够看到
what was right in front of them for decades.
数十年来一直都在眼前的东西
It was right there,apparent evident,waiting to be discovered,
它就在那里 显而易见 等待着被发现
but they completely missed it.
但是他们完全忽略了
Smart,well-intentioned,well-funded,
他们聪明 动机良好 资金充足
but also didn't ask the right question.
但是仍然没有提出正确的问题
Questions create reality. They create possibilities.
问题制造现实 它们制造可能性
A question begins a quest.
一个问题引起一场探索
What they did in positive psychology again,
他们在积极心理学方面的成就...
a great deal through the work of Antonovsky was move us
其中很大部分都是通过Antonovsky的努力
from the pathogenic model to the salutogenic model.
就是让我们从致病模型转到有益健康模型
Salutogenesis,the foundation,the origin of health.
健康本源学 健康的基础 起源
And Antonovsky was talking about,
据Antonovsky所说
he said that it's important to study illness,
研究疾病很重要
mental illness,physical illness,
不管是精神疾病还是身体疾病
but it's equally important to study the healthy people,
但是研究健康的人也同样重要
the healthy individuals to see how they make it,
看看他们为什么会如此健康
whether it's people at Harvard.
不管是否是哈佛大学里的人
Harvard is a stressful environment.
哈佛大学是一个压力非常大的环境
However,there are some people who are able to go through it,
但是有些人却能走完它
to do well,to thrive,flourish and--
表现优秀 茁壮成长
well still going through the ups and downs,
他们也经历起起伏伏
we all do-- overall experience it
我们都是这样 但是总体上
as a much more positive experience as a happy experience overall.
他们的经历更积极更快乐
How do they do that? Why?
他们是如何做到的?为什么?
Antonovsky said we need to study that
Antonovsky说我们要研究这点
so that we understand the origin of health.
这样我们就能了解健康的本源
And he studied these things
他研究了这些东西
and it made a big difference in the field as a whole.
而且它在该领域产生了很大影响
Quote Antonovsky: "All those familiar with the history of science
Antonovsky说"那些熟悉科学史的人"
are aware thatimportant advances come
"都知道重要的进步"
with the formulation of the new questions.
"伴随着新问题的形成而来"
The question is the breakthrough;
"问题才是突破点"
the answer comes with difficulty,
"答案来之不易"
but it is the new question that is important.
"但重要的是新问题"
The salutogenic question,
"有益健康问题"
I submit to you,(that is what is working)
"也就是我向你传播的"(正在发生)
is a radically new question,
"是一个极为新颖的问题"
which provides the impetus for formulating a new paradigm
"它推动新范式的形成"
to help us understand health and illness.
"以帮助我们了解健康和疾病"
It has serious implications for researcher and clinician,
"它对研究人员和医生有着重要意义"
biological and social scientist alike."
"生物学家和社会科学家也是如此"
It was that question that essentially created the field of
正是那个问题缔造了
positive psychology as well as positive sociology.
积极心理学和积极社会学
He was a sociologist by training as well as many other fields.
他是训练有素的社会学家和其他领域的专家
Questions make a difference.
问题导致改变
Questions create reality.
问题缔造现实
I want to do an exercise with you now.
现在我想和你们做一个练习
We'll do quite a few exercises in class.
我们在课堂上会做一些练习
Here's the first one.
这是第一个
To illustrate the importance of question,
为了阐明问题的重要性
now I'm going to ask you to count the number of geometric shapes
我要让你数几何图形的个数
that you see on the screen--
你在屏幕上看到多少个...
no,not this screen,
不 不是这个屏幕
the next screen.
是下一个屏幕
And you are Harvard students. It's fine.
你们是哈佛大学的学生 没问题的
The next screen,
下一个屏幕
I am going to ask you to count the number of geometric shapes
我要让你们数几何图形的个数
that you see on the screen. It's a very difficult question.
你在屏幕上看到的 这是个非常难的问题
I've given it to people around the world.
我把它给世界各地的人看过
I've given it to mathematicians,to artists who are very visual.
我让数学家和视觉艺术家看过
And the challenge here is you are only going to
这里的挑战是
have 30 seconds in which to do it,
你只有30秒去看它
30 seconds to tell me how many geometric shapes
30秒之后告诉我你在屏幕上你看到了
you see on the screen.
多少个几何图形
Ready? 30 seconds.
准备好了吗?30秒
How many geometric shapes do you see on the screen?
你看到屏幕上有多少个几何图形?
Go.
开始
Ok. So that's 31 seconds.
好的 31秒过去了
So there should be no problem.
应该没有问题了
Now if you haven't done-
如果你没有做过...
I know a couple of you have done this exercise before,
我知道你们有些人做过这个练习
but if you haven't done- this exercise before,
但是如果你以前没做过这个练习
-- and that's most of you,
应该是大多数人
I'd like you to participate.
我希望你们能参与其中
So how many geometric shapes could you count on the screen?
你数出了屏幕上的多少个图形?
Throw out the numbers.
把数字说出来
6. 8. 48. 58. 44. 36. 110. 38.
6 8 48 58 44 36 110 38
How many?
多少?
Up there?
上面呢?
You have a good perspective.
你们的视角很好
8. Anyone more than 110?
8 有多于110个的吗?
Yeah,how many? 300?
好的 多少?300?
200. Anyone more than 200 or less than 6?
200 有多于200个或少于6个的吗?
Ok. So quite a range.
好的 很大的范围
But I grant you that it's a tough question.
但是我承认这是个很难的问题
By the way if you have it on your power points
顺便说一下 如果你下载的PPT上
that you downloaded,
有这幅图...
I took it off on the later downloading,
后来我取消下载了
but if you downloaded it,
但是如果你下载了它
don't look at it now please.
请现在不要看
So we have the rate between 6 and 200.
数到的个数在6个到200个之间
Now it's a tough question.
这是一个很难的问题
In fact,
实际上
it is so tough that I have no idea how many geometric shapes
它难到我根本不知道有多少个几何图形
there are on the screen.
在屏幕上
But I have another question for you.
但是我有另一个问题要问你们
Now if you know the answer to this question,
如果你知道这个问题的答案
just put your hand up
就把手举起来
--and if you haven't done this exercise before,
如果你以前没做过这个练习
-- just put your hand up. Don't shout it out.
就把手举起来 别说出来
If you know the answer,put your hand up:
如果你知道答案 把手举起来
what time was it on the clock?
时钟上显示的是几点钟?
If you know the answer,put your hand up.
如果你知道答案就把手举起来
If you think you know the answer,half way up.
如果你认为你知道答案 举一半
Maybe maybe,quarter.
也许知道 举四分之一
And the rest of you may leave now.
剩下的可以离开了
Ok,so we have a few halves. So out of the room,
有几个举了一半 所以在整个教室里
--how many were there-- probably 600,700 students here,
这里有多少...这里大概有六七百个学生
out of 700 Harvard students,
在七百个哈佛学生里
five and a half people can read the time on the clock.
五个半人能看到时钟上的时间
But I understand,we all have digital watches today.
但是我知道 我们今天都有电子表
It's difficult.
这很困难
So let me ask you an easier question.
我来问你们另一个较容易的问题
If you know the answer,just put your hand up.
如果你知道答案就把手举起来
That's right!
没错
How many kids were visible on the bus?
你看到巴士上有多少个小孩?
If you know the answer,put your hand up.
如果你知道答案 把手举起来
If you think you know,half way up.
如果你觉得你知道 举一半
Maybe,quarter.
也许知道 举四分之一
Yeah,most of you think,"what bus?!"
大多数人都在想"什么巴士?"
You know. "What kids?"
"什么小孩?"
Well it was there.
就在那里
So out of a room of --again -- 700 Harvard students,
整个教室里的七百个哈佛学生
there are approximately 11 and 3/4. Who can count?
大概有11.75人数出来了
But that's Ok.
但那没关系
That's not my 55 (Math 55 course in Harvard) here.
这不是55号数学课程
I understand.
我明白
Another question.
另一个问题
A little bit easier.
它比较容易
What was the color of,the dominant color of
屏幕上最左边的几何图形
the left-most geometric shape on the screen?
它的主要颜色是什么?
Not the big one on screen,
不是较大的那个图形
but the left-most geometric shape on the screen.
而是屏幕上最左边的几何图形
What was the dominant color?
主要颜色是什么?
If you know the answer,hand right up.
如果你知道答案 把手举起来
If you think you know,half way.
如果觉得自己知道 举一半
Ok. So that's about 12 1/4 people.
好的 大概是12.25人
According to my estimated research,
根据我的估计研究
there are probably between 5 and 7 people in this room
这个教室里大概有五到七人
who are color blind.
是色盲的
Really-- according to the statistics.
真的 根据统计资料
The rest of you have no excuse.
其余的人则没有借口说看不清
Let's look.
我们来看看
So the time on the clock?
时钟上显示的时间?
Someone difficult to obscure the time?
有谁觉得很难看清时间吗?
10:10.
十点十分
Well it's a bit difficult.
这是有点难
Visible children on the bus?
可以看见车上有多少个小孩?
Here's the bus,for those of you still can't see it.
汽车在这里 有些人还是看不见
5. And the color.
五个 还有颜色
The dominant color of the geometric shape?
最左边几何图形的主要颜色?
Yellow.
黄色
What happened?
怎么回事?
I mean these are not very difficult questions.
这是说 这些并不是非常难的问题
Even the final of positive psychology
就算是积极心理学的期末考
is going to be difficult than that.
都要比它难
I mean,really. A lot more.
真的 难很多
Why?
为什么?
Well the reason is I asked you a certain question,
原因是 我问了你们某个特定的问题
and that question directed you to a certain part of reality.
那个问题让你注意现实的某一部分
And that's a good thing.
这是件好事
Because if we were focusing on everything all the time,
因为如果我们总是专注于一切事情
that wouldn't be a good thing.
那就不是件好事
We would be distracted by every single noise,
每种噪音都会让我们分心
by every single movement.
所有物体运动都会让我们分心
So it's a good thing that we can focus.
所以我们能集中注意力是件好事
However,we also need to remember
但是 我们也要记得
the consequences of this ability to focus
这种集中精神的能力带来的后果
that is not always good it's not always helpful.
却不总是好事或者有益的
Because as far as you were concerned,
因为在你们看来
there were no children on the bus.
巴士上没有小孩
As far as you were concerned,
在你们看来
there were only geometric shapes.
上面只有几何图形
In other words,my question,for most of you,
换句话说 我的问题给你们大多数人
created a very specific reality,
制造了一种特定的现实
a reality which there were geometric shapes
一种只有几何图形
and no children on the bus.
巴士上没有小孩的现实
Now that has very important implications.
这有着非常重要的含义
Think about the following question: what question is mostly asked
想想以下的问题 蜜月期过后
by couples beyond the honeymoon phase?
夫妻间问的最多的问题是什么?
so they go through the honeymoon phase
他们度过蜜月期之后
whether it's a month,a year or sometimes two years.
不管是一个月 一年还是两年
What questions do they begin to ask after that period of time?
那段时期后他们会开始问什么问题?
"What's wrong? What's not working?
"怎么回事?有什么问题?"
How can we improve the relationship?"
"我们怎样去改善关系?'
Now that's a very important question to ask.
这是一个非常重要的问题
Very important.
非常重要
But if that's the only question
但如果这是我们所问的
or the only questions that we ask,
唯一一些问题
then that is the only thing we will see.
那么我们看到的也只有这件事
The only things that we will see are our deficiencies,
我们能看到的只是我们的不足
the things that are not working,
出了差错的事情
the things that need to be improved,
需要去改善的事情
the weaknesses of my partner,
我伴侣的缺点
of the relationship.
我们关系的缺点
If the only questions that I ask are "what is not working",
如果我只是问"什么出了差错"
"what's wrong","what do I need to improve"-- and again,
"怎么回事 我要改善什么" 重申一次
these are not questions we need to do away with,
我们不需要去掉这些问题
they are important. However if they are the only questions,
它们很重要 但如果它们是唯一的问题
and usually they are the only questions
而通常它们确实是
that are asked or primarily asked,
被提出或主要提出的问题
then as far as the couple is concerned,not objectively,
那么在这对夫妇看来 不是客观上
but as far as the couple is concerned,
在这对夫妇看来
good things do not exist in the relationship.
他们的关系里没有好的事物
Just like as far as you are concerned,
就像在你们看来
there were no children on the bus,
巴士上没有小孩
even though they were right there in front of you,
虽然他们就在你们面前
staring at you.
盯着你
But they do not exist.
但是他们不存在
Or think about it at an individual level.
或者从个人的角度思考它
This is very important.
这非常重要
What is the question that we,
我们问得最多的问题...
most Americans,most Australians,most Chinese,
大多数美国人 澳大利亚人 中国人
most Israelis,most Europeans,Africans--
以色列人 欧洲人 非洲人
what is the question that is mostly asked about the self?
大多数人最经常问自己的是什么问题?
And the reason why I mentioned all these places
我之所以要提到那些地方
is because this is cross-cultural study.
是因为这是跨文化的研究
People mostly ask themselves,
大多数人都会问自己
"what are my weaknesses? What do I need to improve?"
我的弱点是什么?我要改善什么?
Very often to the exclusion of
通常排除了
"what are my strengths? What are my virtues? What am I good at?"
我的长处是什么?我擅长于什么?
And if the only question
如果我们问自己的
that we ask ourselves are the only questions that are
唯一问题是
"what are my weaknesses? Deficiencies?",
我的缺点 我的不足是什么?
then the only thing we'll see in ourselves
那么我们能看到的
are weaknesses and deficiencies.
只有自己的缺点和不足
And as far as we are concerned,
在我们看来
the good things-- our strengths,our passions,our virtues--
好的东西 我们的长处 热情 美德
the wonderful things within us do not exist.
我们身上的美好事物并不存在
Just like as far as you are concerned,
就像在你们看来
the children on the bus did not exist.
巴士上的小孩并不存在
Now I ask you,
现在我问你们
could a person who only or primarily focuses on weaknesses
一个主要关注缺点的人
and does not see,
看不到
does not appreciate their strength,their passions,
也不欣赏他们的长处 热情
their virtues--
他们的美德的人
can a person like that experience high levels of self-respect,
一个这样的人会有很高的自尊心
self-confidence,happiness?
自信心和很多的快乐吗?
And we wonder,why do so many relationships fail?
我们还奇怪 为什么这么多婚姻会失败?
And we wonder,why depression,anxiety
我们还奇怪 为什么抑郁 焦虑
and low self-esteem are increasing so much?
以及自尊心低落的情况增加了这么多?
The intentions are there.
动机是有的
They are good. We are asking
它们都是好的动机 我们问的是
"How can we improve? What can we do better?"
"我们如何改善?怎样才能做得更好?"
But if we don't also ask the positive question,
但如果我们不问积极的问题
that part of reality will not exist as far as we are concerned.
在我们看来那部分现实并不存在
Just like for the psychologists for decade,
就像数十年来对那些心理学家一样
the answer to their questions,the solution to the problem
他们问题的答案 问题的解决方案
that they wanted to solve did not exist,
并不存在
even though it is right there,
即使它就在那里
in front of their very eyes within the successful kids,
在他们的眼前 在那些成功孩子的身上
within their resilience.
在他们的心理弹性里
Questions create reality.
问题缔造现实
The questions we ask very often determine
我们所问的问题通常决定了
the quest that we will pursue,
我们追求的东西
the path that we will take,
我们会走的道路
the life that we will lead,
我们会过的生活
whether it's individually,
不管是从个人方面来说
whether it's interpersonally,
从人际关系方面来说
whether it's organizationally.
从组织方面来说都是这样
What is the question?
什么问题...
Many of you I know are going into consulting.
我知道你们很多会要当心理辅导师
What's the question that most consultants ask,
心理辅导师最经常问的问题是什么?
Either explicit question or implicit question,
不管他们是否说出来
the first time when they meet a client?
他们首次见到客户问的问题是什么?
--"What's wrong? What can we improve?
"有什么问题?有什么需要改善的?"
What are the weaknesses that we need to strengthen them?"
"有什么缺点需要改正?"
Again,important questions to ask.
再说一次 它们是很重要的问题
But if you only ask these questions,
但如果你只问这些问题
then you are ignoring the strengths,
那么你就忽视了这个机构的
the virtues of the organization.
优势以及美德
And what you are doing,you are enervating,
你所做的只是在让他们失去活力
you are weakening the organization over time.
你在让公司慢慢地变弱
It is as important,if not more important,
欣赏起作用的东西
to also appreciate what is working,
也同样重要 如果不是更重要的话
organizationally,interpersonally,as well as individually.
不管是在机构里 人际关系里或个人方面
It is important to appreciate what is good.
欣赏好的事物非常重要
I mean,look at the word,"appreciate".
看看"Appreciate"这个词
Two meanings: first meaning-- to say thank you for something,
它有两个意思 其一就是为某事感激
not to take it for granted.
而不是认为某事理所当然
And that's a nice thing to do.
这样做很好
We shouldn't take for granted our virtues,our successes.
我们不应该把长处 成功看作理所当然
We shouldn't take for granted others.
我们不应把别人看作理所当然
That's a nice thing to do.
这是很好的事情
But appreciate has a second meaning,which is to grow.
但是"Appreciate"还有一个意思就是增值
Money appreciates in the bank.
钱在银行里会增值
The economy hopefully appreciates.
经济会增长
When we appreciate the good,
当我们感激好的东西
the good appreciates-- the good grows.
好的东西便会增值 它会增长
Unfortunately,the other side of the same coin applies as well.
不幸的是 反过来也是成立的
When we don't appreciate the good,
当我们不感激好的东西
when we take it for granted,the good depreciates.
把它看作理所当然 好的东西会贬值
And that's what happens in most relationships
那就是大多数婚姻
after the honeymoon phase.
蜜月期后发生的情况
That's what happens to most people,
那就是发生在多数人身上的情况
especially to very driven people who want to improve,
特别是对于那些有动力去提高
who want to get better.
想变得更好的人
And that's good thing,
那是件好事
if that is what makes you happy.
如果那让你感到开心的话
At the same time,
同时
it's equally important to also appreciate what is good inside me
欣赏自己的优点也同样重要
what my strengths,what my virtues are.
我的长处 优点是什么
And we are going to do a lot of that in the course.
我们在课堂中将经常练习这点
And again,not to go to the point of narcissism.
但是不会做到自我陶醉的程度
If anything narcissism-- and we'll talk about it
我们会谈到自我陶醉
in the second last lecture in the semester-
就在本学期倒数第二节课
narcissism is not about self-confidence,about self-esteem.
自我陶醉不是自信 不是自尊
It's exactly the opposite.
它正好相反
We are talking about grounded self-confidence.
我们说的是有根据的自信
Grounded,generous,benevolent happiness.
有根据的大方有益的快乐
In order to lead that kind of life,
为了过上那种生活
we need to also appreciate what is working,
我们还要欣赏起作用的东西
to also focus on,metaphorically speaking,the children on a bus.
用比喻的意义上说 还要留意巴士上的小孩
Stavros and Torres in the wonderful book on relationships,
Stavros和Torres在一本关于婚姻的好书里说
"We see what we look for and we miss much of
"我们会看到要寻找的东西"
what we are not looking for even though it is there.
"错失不去寻找的东西 虽然它在那里"
Our experience of the world is heavily influenced
"我们的阅历"
by where we place our attention."
"被我们的关注点深深地影响了"
Questions very often create reality.
问题经常会缔造现实
The first important thing to understand about questions
理解什么是问题的首要事情
is that we need to understand the questions.
就是我们要理解那些问题
And here I want to defer to a very important philosopher,
在这点我同意一位重要哲学家
a 20th and 21st century philosopher,
一位20世纪和21世纪的哲学家
who illustrates the importance of understanding questions--
他阐明了理解问题的重要性
Homer Simpson.
荷马辛普森
If you can just turn down the voice,the sound a little bit,
能不能把声音调低一点
because this is very loud. Thank you.
因为它非常大声 谢谢
The Simpsons
辛普森一家
SCULLY: Now we're gonna run a few tests.
(第810集)
现在我们要做几项测试
This is a simple lie detector.
这是一台简单的测谎仪
I'll ask you a few yes or no questions
我会问你几个问题 你回答是或否
and you just answer truthfully.
你要老实回答
Do you understand?
明白吗?
HOMER: Yes.
明白
Love it. Love it.
很精彩
So the first step is really understanding the question.
所以第一步是真正理解问题
But once we understand it,
但是我们理解问题之后
it is also important to know what questions are we going to ask.
知道我们要问什么问题也很重要
I mentioned earlier that one of the most important things
我之前提到过培养心理弹性的要事之一
in cultivating resilience is having a role model.
就是要有一个榜样
I want to share with you now my role model,
现在我要告诉你们我的榜样
in fact,the person who is the reason
实际上 正是因为她
why I decided to become a teacher.
我才决定成为一名教师
Her name is Marva Collins.
她叫Marva Collins
Marva Collins was born in Alabama in the 1930s.
Marva Collins20世纪30年代生于阿拉巴马州
Her father was African American; her mother,Native American.
她父亲是非洲裔美国人 母亲是印地安人
she was born at a time in a place
她出生的时候
where there was a great deal of discrimination.
种族岐视风行
Fortunately,for Marva,
幸运的是 对于Marva
her father really believed in her
她父亲对她非常有信心
and said to her from a very young age,
从小他就对她说
"Marva,you can make something of your life.
"Marva 你将会有所作为"
You can become a secretary."
"你可以成为一名秘书"
Now the reason why he said secretary is because
他之说以说秘书是因为
that was where the glass ceiling,
那就是无形的障碍
or rather concrete ceiling exists
或者说是有形的障碍
for a person of her ethnic background,
鉴于她的种族背景
a person of her gender.
鉴于她的性别
Marva Collins worked hard.
Marva Collins努力工作
She was smart. She succeeded. She made it.
她很聪明 她成功了
And she became a secretary.
她成为了一名秘书
After a few years of working as a secretary,doing well,
做了几年秘书之后 虽然干得不错
she decided this was not for her and what her calling in life.
她觉得这不适合她 不是她的使命
Her real passion was in teaching.
她真正的热情在于教书
She wanted to be a school teacher.
她想成为学校里的一名教师
She went to night school.
于是她上夜校
A few years later,
几年之后
she got her teaching certificate,
她得到了教师证书
got married and with her husband moved to Chicago.
她结婚了并和丈夫搬到了芝加哥
There she joined the public school system in inner city,Chicago.
她在那加入了芝加哥内城的公立学校
The reality that she found,
她在那里看到的现实
that she encountered there was a reality of much crime,
是大量犯罪
much drugs and more than anything,hopelessness.
毒品泛滥 最重要的是没有希望
The hope of the teachers was to keep the students in school
老师们的希望是让孩子们
for as long as possible.
在学校里尽可能呆久点
Why? --So that they don't join the street gangs at the age of 12;
为什么?因为这样他们就不会12岁加入街头帮派
so that they are protected from the drugs,from crime.
这样他们就不会接触毒品 不会犯罪
"How can we keep the students in school for as long as possible?"
"我们怎样让学生呆在学校里?"
asked the teachers.
老师们问
Marva Collins walks into this reality and says,
Marva Collins面对这种现实说
"Things are going to be different."
"事情将有所改观"
On the first day of class,
在上课的第一天...
-- she teaches first graders to fourth graders--
她教一年级到四年级
--on the first day of class,
在上课的第一天
she says to her students,
她对学生们说
"We are going to do a lot of believing in ourselves."
"我们要练习自信"
And she repeats this message over and over and over again,
她不断地重复地说着这则信息
like a broken record throughout the semester
整个学期犹如不断重播的唱片
and the year and years.
最后坚持了整年 几年
"I believe in you. You can do well. You can succeed.
"我相信你 你能做好 你能成功"
Take responsibility for your life.
"承担生活的责任"
Stop blaming. Stop blaming the government.
"停止抱怨 停止抱怨政府"
Stop blaming your teachers. Stop blaming your parents.
"停止抱怨老师 停止抱怨父母"
It is up to you to succeed."
"成功与否全在你自己"
And she continues with this message over and over and over again.
她继续不断地重复着这则信息
Having really high expectations of her students,
她对学生们充满期望
looking at what they are good at,
把眼光放在他们的长处
their strength and cultivating those.
和优点上 并而加以培养
Miracles begin to happen. These students,
奇迹开始发生了
considered by many of the teachers to be"unteachable"-
这些被老师认为是"不可教"的学生
these "unteachable" ones by the time that they are in
到了四年级便可以读
fourth grade are reading Euripides,Emerson and Shakespeare.
欧里庇得斯 爱默生和莎翁的作品
These "unteachable" ones at the age of 10
这些"不可教"的学生在十岁时
are doing high school mathematics.
便可以做高中的数学
Now rumor begins to spread about Marva Collins,
关于Marva Collins的谣言开始传播
because how can she keep these students in class for so long,
她怎能让这些学生在教室里呆这么长时间
when all the other students are just trying to get out of school?
而其他学生却想着离开学校?
She must be using force.
她一定是在强迫他们
And Marva Collins has enough of these rumors,
Marva Collins受够了谣言的中伤
leave the public school system,opens up her own school
她离开公共学校成立了自己的学校
in her own kitchen with 4 students and initially,
就在她的厨房里 开始只有四个学生
two of them her own kids.
其中两个是她的孩子
Gradually,more and more students join the Marva Collins school,
逐渐地 越来越多的学生进入了Marva Collins学校
Westside preparatory she calls it.
她称之为西岸小学
All the students that initially joined the school
一开始进入这间学校的学生
are public school dropouts.
都是从公共学校退学的
Marva Collins is the last resort before the street.
Marva Collins是他们成为街头混混前最后的希望
And the miracles continue.
奇迹继续发生
Gradually more and more students come in.
逐渐地 越来越多的学生进入
She has to move out of her home.
她不得不搬出去
They wretchedly rent a small shack in Chicago place,
他们在芝加哥租了一间小室
freezing in winter,scorching hot in summer.
冬天寒冷无比 夏天酷热难当
And yet the students are driven by their passion.
然而学生们被他们的热情所驱动
And they continue. Miracles continue to happen to them.
他们继续学习 奇迹继续发生在他们身上
Every one of Marva Collins' students graduates
Marva Collins所有的学生
from elementary school.
都从小学毕业了
Everyone goes to high school and graduates from high school.
所有学生都上了高中并毕业了
Every one of her students ends up in college
她所有的学生最后都上了大学
and graduates from college.
并从大学毕业
Yes,those "unteachable" ones.
没错 那些"不可教"的学生
Marva Collins lives in a dire poverty for decades,
Marva Collins数十年生活困苦
somehow making ends meet.
然而她努力平衡收支
After all,most of her students can't pay.
毕竟 她的学生都无法付学费
But somehow,months to months,she makes it.
但是 月继一月 她熬过去了
1979 it changes overnight.
1979年 情况一夜发生了变化
A producer,from the television CBS program "60 Minutes" finds
CBS《60分钟》的制片人
out about Marva Collins and creates a 15 minutes segment on her.
得知了Marva Collins的故事 并制作了15分钟的节目
Overnight she becomse famous.
她一夜成名
November,1980,
1980年11月
new President elect Ronald Reagan calls up Marva Collins.
新当选总统罗纳德里根打电话给Marva Collins
offers her to be his secretary of Education.
请她做他的教育部长
So I guess her father was right.
我想她父亲是对的
Marva Collins turns his offers down and says,
Marva Collins拒绝了邀请 她说
"I love to teach too much. My place is in the classroom.
"我太喜欢教书了 我属于教室"
8 years later almost to the day,
恰好八年过去了
new president elect George Bush Sr.
新当选总统老布什
calls Marva Collins once again,
再次打电话给Marva Collins
offering her to be his secretary of education.
请她做他的教育部长
Once again,"I love to teach too much."
再一次 她说"我太喜欢教书了"
My place is in the classroom.
"我属于教室"
In 1995,a wealthy philanthropist donates tens of millions
1995年 一位富裕的慈善家捐赠了
of dollars to Marva Collins.
数千万美元给Marva Collins
Now there are Marva Collins schools all over the country
现在全国都有Marva Collins学校
where thousands of students learn,
数千名学生在里面学习
where hundreds of teachers from all over the world
来自世界各地的数百名教师
come and see the miracle of Marva Collins.
前来目睹Marva Collins的奇迹
Today there are Marva Collins graduates who are politicians,
今天Marva Collins的学生里有政治家
business people,lawyers,doctors,
商人 律师 医生
and more than anything,teachers.
而最多的 就是老师
Because they know what their teacher has done for them.
因为他们知道他们老师的功劳
I want to show you a brief excerpt of this extraordinary woman.
我要展示这位杰出女性的一个片段
You can turn the volume up a little bit please.
请把声音调大一点
This is soft.
它声音不大
Marva Collins "Positive Learning"
Marva Collins"积极学习法"
I think I did pretty wonderful.
我想我做得很好
I think I'm bright. I think I am unique.
我想我很聪明 我很特别
And I'll teach every child of me to think that.
我会教每个孩子这样想
When they misbehave,
当他们不守规矩的时候
their punishment is they have to write 100 reasons
他们的惩罚就是要写100个原因
why they are too wonderful to do what they are doing.
说明为什么他们棒到要做那样的事
And they have to be alpha order.
而且它们要按字母顺序写
I am adorable. I am beautiful. I am courageous.
我很可爱 我很漂亮 我很勇敢
I give them the first ones until they get the hang out of it.
我给他们例子直到他们明白
I am delightful. I am effervescent. I am fabulous.
我令人快乐 我很兴奋 我很厉害
I am heavenly. I am idolized. I am just wonderful.
我很棒 我是榜样 我无与伦比
I am a kindred spirit. I am lovable. I am momentous.
我很热情 我很可爱 我很重要
I am never,never indolent.
我从不懒惰
And it goes on to z. And if they do it again,
一直写到最后一个字母 如果他们再犯
then they have to use another synonym.
他们必须要用另一个同义词
They can't use adorable any more.
他们不能再用可爱了
Now the children will say to a new student,
现在孩子们会对新学生说
I know why you don't behave.
我知道你为什么不再不守规矩了
Coz I'm tired of telling Ms. Collins how wonderful I am.
因为我厌倦告诉Ms. Collins我有多棒了
Now she is wonderful.
她非常棒
Here is her book.
这是她的书
Now for all those-- I know that
对于那些...我知道
there are quite a few of you who are interested in teaching,
你们中有些人对教书有兴趣
and there's one book you want to read. It's this.
如果有一本你要读的书 就是这本
For all those of you who are interested in leadership
对于那些对做领导有兴趣的人
and there's one book you want to read. It's this.
如果有一本你要读的书 就是这本
For all those of you who are or are interested in the future
对于那些已经是或以后想做父母的人
of becoming parents,and there's one book you want to read.
如果有一本你要读的书
It's this.
就是这本
For all the rest of you,
对于剩下的人
if there's one book you want to read.
如果有一本你要读的书...
So what's her message?
她传递的信息是什么?
First of all,
首先
she herself is the message as a role model.
她本身就是榜样
And she studied with her kids,role models.
她和孩子们学习榜样
They read fiction books. They read historical books.
他们读小说 历史书
They read books about heroes and talk about heroes.
他们读关于英雄的书 谈论英雄的事
They all identify role models.
他们都认清了谁是榜样
They identify role models in their neighborhood,
他们从社区里挑出榜样
in their families,constantly doing that,
在家庭里挑出榜样 不断地这样做
which is exactly what you need to cultivate resilience.
这就是你培养心理弹性要做的事
First and foremost,she herself is the role model.
首先 她就是榜样
She has high expectations.
她有着很高的期望
We are going to do a lot of believing in ourselves.
我们要大量练习自信
We are going to do well,succeed.
我们要表现优秀 我们要成功
She expects a lot.She sees the potential.
她有很多期待 她能看到潜力
She appreciates that potential in each individual.
她欣赏每个人的潜力
Stop blaming others. Take responsibility for your life.
停止抱怨别人 承担自己生活的责任
Marva Collins is no push-over.
Marva Collins并不是软弱的人
If you see her in the classroom,she is tough. She is demanding.
教室里的她要求很严格
At the same time,she respects each individual.
同时 她尊重每个人
She is not one of the Pollyannish "feel-good",
她不是不切实际的"感觉良好"
"let's make them all feel good" at all cost.
我们不惜一切代价让他们感觉良好
Not at all.
根本不是
She believes in them.She respects them.
她相信他们 她尊重他们
And she is tough and demanding--
而且她要求很严格
important combination for leadership.
这是领导的重要因素
It's why I mentioned earlier
这就是为什么我之前提到
in the context of great leadership book.
它是一本好的领导书籍
There are many very nice ex-CEOs
有很多非常和善的前总裁
whose primary aim was to be nice and to be liked,
他们的主要目标就是和善和受欢迎
the keys to get the job done,
完成工作的关键
to get the work done,
完成事情的关键
while being respectful.
同时也要尊重他人
Sense of optimism.
她有乐观精神
You can do well.
你可以做好
You are going to do well,
你会做得很好
helping them set goals for themselves and for community.
帮助他们为自己和社区设立目标
And finally,
最后
from focusing on deficiencies to focusing on strength.
从专注缺点到专注优点
Howard Gardner from the ED(Education) school here talks about
来自教育学校的Howard Gardner
multiple intelligences,says that we need to stop asking
谈到了多元智力 他说我们要停止问
whether or not a student is smart.
一个学生是否聪明
What we need to ask is what is the student smart at.
我们要问这个学生有什么优点
And when we identify what that student is smart at,
认清这个学生的优点
strong at,virtuous at,good at,then we appreciate it.
长处之后 我们便欣赏它
And when we appreciate it,
当我们欣赏它的时候
it and the whole person appreciates.
优点和那整个人都会增值
What would happen to a seed-- seed is potential--
假如有一粒种子...种子是有潜力的
flower,tree-- what would happen to a seed,
它会长成花草树木...假如有一粒种子
if it is not watered,if no light is shed on it?
如果它没有受到灌溉 没有阳光照耀会怎样?
It will wither and die.
它会枯萎死去
The exact same thing with human potential.
人类的潜力也是这样
If we don't water it,if we don't shed a light on it,
如果我们不灌溉它 如果我们不照耀它
it will wither and die.
它会枯萎死去
The same with interpersonal relationship potential.
人际关系也是这样
If we don't-- we'll talk a lot about relationships:
如果我们...我们会经常谈到关系
how to cultivate healthy long-term relationships--
如何培养健康长期的关系
if you don't water it,if you don't shed light,
如果你不灌溉它 不照耀它
if you don't appreciate the good,the good will depreciate.
如果你不欣赏它的好处 好处就会贬值
Essentially,
本质上
what Marva Collins does is create for students--
Marva Collins所做的
what the research in resilience does is
也就是心理弹性的作用就是
create a very different model than the conventional wisdom.
缔造一个与传统智慧不同的榜样
The paradigm shift essentially is from being a passive victim
范式转移实质上是从被动接受者...
because the government is not putting enough money,
也就是政府没有投入足够资金
which is an issue,not belittling it.
这是一个问题 应该重视
It's important to have those external
用外部条件 比如资源
affect the internal like more resources.
影响内在性格很重要
But that's not enough.
但那并不足够
From an inactive,from a passive victim,
从一个不积极 被动的受害者
she changes her perspective to be an active agent.
成为一个主动的人 她改变了看法
You are not "unteachable".
你并非"不可教"
You can thrive. You can do well.You can succeed.
你可以发展 你可以做好 你可以成功
And what she does,essentially,
而她所做的实质上
is take them to the extreme of continuum,because every event,
就是把他们带到连续体的极点
every person can be situated somewhere along this continuum,
因为每件事每个人都处于连续体的某处
I mean different places with different things.
我是说 不同的地方和不同的事物
Think about your own life.
想想你自己的生活
What are you,
你是哪种人?
passive victim in different situations or an active agent?
各种情况的被动受害者还是主动者?
For example,let's say my girlfriend leaves me.
例如 假如说我女朋友离开了我
I know when I was an undergrad here.
当我还是这里的学生的时候
This was top on my mind: girlfriends leaving me.
我主要想的是 我女朋友要离开我了
Yes.
是的
We'll talk about that later in this semester
那点我们以后再谈
when we get to know one another a little bit better.
当我们熟悉彼此之后
I'm a little bit shy at this point.
现在我有点害羞
But let's say my girlfriend leaves me.
但是假如我女朋友离开了我
If I am the passive victim,what I experience is self-pity.
如果我是被动受害者 那我只会自怜
Feel sorry for myself. ruminate-- remember the word?
为自己感到难过 思考
Ruminate about the situation and how terrible it is.
思考这种情况以及它有多糟糕
From a passive victim,I then move to blame: she's terrible;
我从一个被动受害者变成抱怨者 她很糟糕
it's her fault; I blame her;
都是她的错 我怨她
I blame my parents,the way they raise me;
我抱怨我的父母 他们养育不当
I blame her parents; I blame President Bush or whomever.
我抱怨她的父母 我抱怨布什总统
And after I blame,I experience frustration as well as anger.
抱怨之后 我变得沮丧和愤怒
Anger toward her,toward my parents,her parents,
对她生气 对我父母生气 对她父母生气
President Bush,Hilary,whoever it is. I feel anger.
布什总统 希拉里 总之我很愤怒
And results-- very few results.
结果呢 很少结果
Because I wallow in illumination and self-pity.
因为我沉迷于反思和自怜中
Let's take the other extreme of the active agent.
我们再反观积极主动者
First of all,by definition,I take action.
首先 从定义来看 我会行动
I take responsibility.
我承担责任
I go on to places after experiencing the pain--
经历痛苦之后我会到处走走
it's painful,and next time we are going to talk about
它很痛苦 下节课我们会谈谈
the importance of experiencing the pain of giving ourselves
经历痛苦的重要性
what I called the permission to be human,
谈谈允许自己人性化
but once I experience it,I take action.
但是我经历痛苦之后 我会行动
I go out there to places where I will meet someone.
我去能认识他人的地方
I go to Pinnochio's (Pizza place at Harvard).
我去匹诺曹(哈佛的比萨店)
Or another meeting place,the Stax in Whitener (?).
或者另一个约会地点
Well I guess things have changed
我想时世变迁了
at Harvard since I was an undergrad.
现在的哈佛和我毕业时的不同了
I take responsibility for it.
我承担责任
And then as a result of that--
这样做的结果是...
and we'll talk about research on self-perception theory,
我们会谈谈自我知觉理论
research by Daryl Bem.
它是Daryl Bem的研究
We'll talk a lot about it. You don't need to write it down now.
我们会详细讨论它 你不用现在把它写下来
I'll take action and action will increase our level of confidence
我会行动 行动会增加我们的自信
And then more hope and optimism is a result.
结果是更多的希望和乐观
As we talk about belief in self-fulfilling prophecy lecture,
就像在自我应验预言课程中所说的
hope and optimism become a self-fulfilling prophecy.
希望和乐观会变成自我应验预言
I'm much more likely to find someone.
我更容易找到伴侣
I'm certainly much more likely to be happy.
我更可能变得开心
Once again,being an active agent
重申一次 作为积极主动者
does not mean not giving ourselves the time,
并不意味着不给我们自己时间
the space,the permission to experience painful emotions,
空间去让自己感受痛苦的情感
to go through the emotion.
以及摆脱这种情感
Yes,by all means,we go through it. However,
没错 我们一定会摆脱它 然而
what it is also saying is that we need to find the right time--
我们要在适合的时间...
it could be immediately,it could be a day or two later--
它可能是现在 可能是一两天后
to take action,to take responsibility,to do things so that
去行动 去承担责任 去做事情 这样
our confidence levels in our hope and optimism increase.
我们对希望和乐观的自信就会增加
I want to just say a few things about this idea
我要说几件关于
of being an active agent and responsibility.
做一个积极主动者及责任的事
It applies to your life here at Harvard. It is up to you.
它可以融入你的哈佛生活 这取决于你
It is your responsibility to make the most out of
让你的哈佛时光充满意义
your Harvard experiences.
是你的责任
It is your responsibility to make the most out of this class.
从这门课程学尽量多的东西是你的责任
We,the teaching staff,
我们作为教师
are certainly going to create conditions for it.
肯定会为它创造条件
We are going to support you in every way that you need.
我们会以各种方式支持你们
However,ultimately,
然而 最终
it's your responsibility to do it in section.
小组讨论是你们的责任
It's your responsibility to make it.
作出行动是你们的责任
One of the first questions that you'll be asking question
下周你们在小组里
in section next week when they start to meet is
首先要问的问题之一就是
"how can you make this an excellent section?"
"你如何让它成为一个优秀的小组?"
"What can you do?" "what can you bring?
"你能做什么? 你能有什么贡献?"
What strength can you bring into the section
"你能给小组带来什么优势"
so that it's an excellent section?"
"让它成为一个优秀的小组?"
As opposed to blaming,other students,TF,Bush,Clinton,whoever
而不是抱怨其他学生 组长 布什 克林顿
Taking responsibility for it.
你要为它承担责任
There is a wonderful story about responsibility
关于责任 有一个很好的故事
in the book by Nathaniel Branden.
Nathaniel Branden的书里提到了
We are going to read some stuff by Nathaniel Branden
当我们谈到自尊时
when we talk about self-esteem.
我们要读点Nathaniel Branden的东西
Nathaniel Branden talks about six pillars
Nathaniel Branden谈到了六根支柱
six important pillars in self-esteem.
自尊的六根重要支柱
One of those pillars is self-responsibility.
其中一根就是自我负责
People who have high self-esteem take responsibility.
自尊心强的人会承担责任
People who want to cultivate high self-esteem
想培养高自尊心
and create confidence,take responsibility
培养自信的人会承担责任
for their lives and so on.
承担生活的责任等等
So in his workshop,one of the main things that he says
在他的研讨会上 他在书中说到的
there in his book is that understanding that you have to
主要一件事就是 明白你必须
take responsibility for your life is recognizing understanding
为生活承担责任就是理解
that no one is coming.
没人会来
No one is coming to-- the knight in shining armour
没人会来...穿着闪亮铠甲的骑士
who will take you to the happily-ever-after land.
不会来带你到幸福乐园
No one is coming to make your life better for you.
没人会来让你的生活更美好
No one is coming.
没人会来
You are responsible for your life,for your self-confidence,
你为自己的生活负责 获得自信
for your self-esteem,for your happiness.
自尊 幸福
No one is coming.
没人会来
So he was talking about this in one of his workshops
他在研讨会上谈到了这个
that's a three-day workshop.
那是一个为期三天的研讨会
And this was already on the third day
这已经是第三天了
and the workshop was going well.
研讨会进展顺利
The participants were getting a lot out of it.
参与者都学到了很多
And he said,he told them about this idea that no one is coming.
他说 他告诉他们没人会来
And one of the participants raises his hand and says,
其中一名参与者举手说
"Dr. Branden,that's not true."
"Branden博士 事实并非这样"
And Nathaniel Branden asks him,"What do you mean?" And he says,
Nathaniel Branden问他"为什么?" 他说
"Dr. Branden,you came",to which Branden responded,
"Branden博士 你来了" Branden回应道
"Yes,I came. But I came to tell you that no one is coming."
"没错 我来了 但我是来告诉你没人会来"
No one is coming.
没人会来
It's up to you to make the most out of this experience,
能否最大限度地从这次经历中获益全在于你
1504,your sections,your Harvard experiences and beyond.
1504号课程 你的小组 你的哈佛经历等等
And we,as the teaching staff,
我们作为教师
can't wait to create the right conditions for that to happen.
我们迫不及待想为之创造适合条件
See you on Thursday.
星期四再见